{
  "reference_number": "12865",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Today's government, with cross-party support, needs to set a minimum reduction target and date to achieve that. It must be a target\n based on scientific analysis, that cannot be tampered with for short-term political gain or economic reprieve. We have submitted as a\n 3-generation family group to emphasis the generational impact and action that will need to be taken urgently for the generations to\n\n come."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The effort to reverse, offset or sequestre a century of human-induced greenhouse gases needs to be effective. Although methan\n has a short-live when comapred to the other green house gasses, the heat it transfers to the atmosphere takes a long time to\n\n remove. Therefore the government must not shy away form a robust methane target for the agricultural sector. If farmers require\n subsidies for offsetting programmes or investment in research to make the transition, we believe that cost must be shared by all to\n stabilise the climate for us all."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Authentic carbon offsetting in less developed countries could be mutually beneficial, especially if it helps those countries side-step\n the high-carbon economy of our country. We would prefer projects that include a cultural, life-style or biodiversity gain for the receiving\n\n country."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The target should be set so it can only be lowered, should the science reviews indicate that a stricter target is required."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is a proven model. The UK has set 3 emission budgets and met the targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Emission budgets may only be able to be revised to meet the target earlier."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We support the Government and the Climate Commission taking the following factors into consideration when advising on and\nsetting budgets: Scientific knowledge regarding climate change (his is the most important factor) Technology relevant to climate\n\nchange Economic circumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy considered in its broadest sense, not just the\ncurrent free-market or financial system, Social justice and the need for a fair and just transition to a low carbon economy, so that\n\npeople on low incomes are not disadvantaged by the changes. Fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation,\npublic spending and public borrowing, with consideration of the long-term goal of moving to an economy that is sustainable within\nresource and environmental constraints and that is not based on the assumption of continual and destructive ‘economic growth’.\n\nEnergy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy supplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, the advice from a stable, scientifically - informed, non-partisan body has been crucial to the progress the UK has made to date."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "This is the proven and transparent model used by the UK."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Commission need to have a range of New Zealanders to make sure the science and the implications of the targets are well -\nunderstood by all parts of our society. There needs to be an ecologist on the panel to advocate for the impact of policies on NZ\n\nindigenous biodiversity."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Adaptation is separate issue to the process of directing governments to lower greenhouse emissions. Adaptation is a costly equity\n\nissue that will consume much of New Zealand's GNP in the decades to The social cost of dislocation and money for rebuilding 5000\nhouseholds in the Christchurch Red Zone is going to be repeated in Dunedin, Wellington, Napier, Westport etc as sea levels and\n\nassociated storm surges increase. Local Councils and Regional Councils need to be fully involved in the implementation and\nadaptation for the climate disruption from the increasing levels of greenhouses gasses. it is gong to be decades before the levels will\nstabilise at a higher level than the pre-industrial natural level."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The bill needs to include all aspects of society and the economy and to ensure that any proposed changes are fair and just and do\nnot fall disproportionately on the least advantaged The urgent need to move away from the current ‘\\endless growth’ model for the\n\neconomy and to foster an economic and social structure that is environmentally sustainable for future generations, as well as fair and\nequitable so that all citizens will support it. The Zero Carbon Act must be just and fair in that it honours Te Tiriti o Waitangi; ensures a\n\njust transition for workers and communities; and avoids passing on the costs to future generations."
    }
  ]
}
